<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_simplePrint.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_simplePrint.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Citizens of Toyland</title>
            <author>H. G. Wells</author>
            <editor role="co-editor">Deanna Stover</editor>
            <editor role="co-editor">Nigel Lepianka</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>co-editor, transcription and encoding</resp>
               <name xml:id="ds">Deanna Stover</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>co-editor</resp>
               <name xml:id="nl">Nigel Lepianka</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2019</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication information</p>        
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="main">Citizens of Toyland</title>
               <author>Herbert George Wells</author>
               <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
               <publisher>Everybody's Magazine</publisher>
               <date>December 1911 vol. XXV, no. 6</date>
               <note type="project">The source text is located on HathiTrust at: "http://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015012320191"</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <revisionDesc>
        <change who="#ds" when="2019-10-31">edited code for "The Toys to Have"</change>
        <change who="#ds" when="2019-10-29">transcribed and began encoding "The Toys to Have."</change>
     </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   
   
   
   
  <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="743"/>
         <div>
            <head type="main" rendition="simple:centre">Citizens of Toyland</head>
            <head type="sub" rendition="simple:centre">by</head>
            <head type ="sub" rendition="simple:centre">H. G. WELLS</head>
            <byline rendition="simple:centre">Author of </byline>
            <byline rendition="simple:centre">"THE NEW MACHIAVELLI."</byline>
            <byline rendition="simple:centre">"TONO BUNGAY,"</byline>
            <byline rendition="simple:centre">etc.</byline>
         </div>
         <div>
            <p>Editor's Note:&#8212;When Mr. H. G. Wells publishes a novel in England, it is a national event.
            Men take sides; for whatever else you may do about Mr. Wells, you can not possibly ignore him. There 
            he is&#8212;the keenest, most critical mind in England&#8212;a mind to which noth-ing human is foreign.
            Probably no man in the world has a greater genius for seeing things as they are, a more vivid, concrete
            sense of what things might be like.</p>
            <p>When such a man joins his little sons to play games on the floor, with the spirit of youth enthroned,
            the result is certain to be fine for the boys&#8212;for all boys and their parents He teaches the boys
            to get more fun out of their toys, teaches them to play new games, with a new appeal. If there are any fathers
            who don't just know how to play with the youngsters, they will find a charming example in this picture of 
            a great man of the nursery.</p>
            <p>And if Mr. Wells also tells how, in romping with the children, he helps them to learn some of their future
            as citizens, and how, with building-blocks and toy soldiers and toy civilians, to plan what cities and 
            civilization might be like, it is a further proof of his genius.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <cb/>
            <p>I</p>
            <p>THE TOYS TO HAVE</p>
            <p><rs type="supplies">THE jolliest indoor games for boys and girls demand a floor, and the home that has no floor upon which games
            may be played falls so far short of happiness. It must be a floor covered with linoleum or cork carpet, so
            that toy soldiers and such like will stand up upon it, and of a color and surface that will take and show
            chalk-marks; the common green-colored cork carpet without a pattern is best of all. It must be no highway to other
            rooms, and well-lit and airy.</rs> Occasionally, alas! it must be scrub-bed&#8212;and then a truce to floor games!</p>
            <p>Upon such a floor may be made an infin-<cb/>itude of imaginative games, not only keep-ing boys and girls
            happy for days together, but building up a framework of spacious and inspiring ideas in them for after life.
            The nation will gain new strength from nur-sery floors. I am going to tell of some of these games and what is most
            needed to play them; I have tried them all and a score of others like them with my sons, and all of the games here
            illustrated have been set out by us. I am going to tell of them here, because I think what we have done will
            interest other fathers and mothers and perhaps be of use to them (and to uncles and such like tributary sub-
            species of hu-manity) in buying presents for their own and other people's children.</p>
            <p>Now the toys we play with time after time and in a thousand permutations and
               combinations belong to four main groups:<pb n="744"/>
               <rs type="supplies"> We have <rs type="soldier">(1) SOLDIERS, and with these I class sailors, railway
                     porters, civilians, and the lower animals generally, such as I will presently
                     describe in greater detail;</rs>
               <rs type="bricks">(2)BRICKS;</rs>
               <rs type="boards">(3) BOARDS AND PLANKS;</rs>
                  and <rs type ="train">(4) a lot of CLOCKWORK RAILWAY ROLLING-STOCK AND
                     RAILS.</rs></rs>
                  Also there are certain other minor objects&#8212;tin ships, Easter eggs,
                  plasticine, and the like&#8212;of which I shall make incidental mention,
                that, like the kiwi and the duck-billed platypus, refuse to be classified.
               These we arrange and rearrange in various ways upon our floor, making a world of
               them. In doing so we have found out all sorts of pleasant facts, and also many
               undesirable possibilities; and very probably our experience will help a reader here
               and there to the former and save him from the latter.</p>
            <p><rs type="boards">For instance, our planks and boards and what we can do with them have been a great discovery. lots of boys and girls seem
            to be quite without planks and boards at all, and there is no regular trade in them. The toy-shops do not keep anything of the
            sort. (We don't, as a matter of fact, think very much of toy-shops. We think they trifle with great possibilities. We consider
            them expensive and incompetent, and flatten our noses against their plate glass perhaps, but only in the most critical spirit.)
            Our boards, which we had to get made by a carpenter, are the basis of half the games we play</rs></p>
            <p><rs type="boards">The planks and boards we have are of various sizes. We began with three of two yards by one, made with cross-pieces like small
            doors; but these we found unneces-sarily large, and we would not get them now after our present experience. The best thickness,
            we think, is an inch for the larger sizes, and three-quarters and a half inch for the smaller; and the best sizes are a yard 
            square, thirty inches square, two feet, and eighteen inches square&#8212;one or two of each, and a greater number of smaller ones,
            18 x 9, 9 x 9, and 9 x 4 1-2.</rs></p>
            <p><rs type="boards">With the larger ones we make islands and archipelagoes on our floor, while the floor is a sea; or we make a larger island, or a 
            couple in the Venice pattern; or we pile the smaller on the larger to make hills when the floor is level plain; or they roof in railway
            stations or serve as bridges, in such manner as I will presently illustrate.</rs> And these boards of ours pass into our next most important
            possession, which is a box of bricks.</p> <cb/>
            <p><rs type="boards">(But I was nearly forgetting to tell this&#8212;that all the thicker and larger of these boards have holes bored through them. At
            about every four inches is a hole, a little larger than an ordinary gimlet hole. THese holes have their uses, as I will tell later; but
            now let me get on to the box of bricks.)</rs></p>
            <p>This again wasn't a toy-shop acquisition. It came to us by gift from two generous friends, unhappily growing up and very tall at that;
            and they had it from parents who were one of several families that shared in the benefit of a good uncle. I know nothing vertainly of this
            man except that he was a Radford of Plymouth. I have never learnt or cared to learn of his commoner occupations, but certainly he was
            one of those shining and distinguished uncles that tower up at times above the common levels of humanity. At times, when we consider
            our derived and undeserved share of his inherit-ance and count the joys it gives us, we have projected half in jest and half in earnest
            the putting together of a little exemplary book upon the subject of such exceptional men. "Celebrated Uncles," it should be called;
            and it should stir up all who read it to some striving, at least, toward the glories of the avuncular crown.</p>
            <p>What this great benefactor did was to engage a deserving, unemployed carpenter through an entire winter making big boxes of wooden
            bricks for the almost innumer-able nephews and nieces with which an appreciative circle of brothers and sisters had blessed him.
            <rs type="bricks">There are whole bricks 4 1-2 x 2 1-4 x 1 1-8 inches; there are half bricks 2 1-4 x 2 1-4 x 1 1-8, and there are quarters&#8212;called
            by those previous owners (who have now ascended to, we hope but scarcely believe, a happier life near the ceiling) "piggys." You note
            how these sizes fit into the sizes of our boards; and of each size&#8212;we have never counted them&#8212;we must have hundreds. We 
            can pave a dozen square yards of floor with them.</rs></p>
            <p>How utterly we despise the silly little bricks of the toy-shops! They are too small to make a decent home for even the poorest
               lead soldiers; even if there were hundred of them&#8212;and there are never enough&#8212;never nearly enough, even if you take
               one at a time and lay it down and say: "This is a house"&#8212;even then there are not enough. We see rich people, rich people
            out in motor-cars, people rich be<pb n="746"/>
            yond the dreams of avarice, going into toy-shops and buying these skimpy, sickly, ridiculous pseudo-boxes of bricklets, be-cause they do
            not know what to ask for, and the toy-shops are just the merciless, mercenary enemies of youth and happiness&#8212;so far, that is, as
            bricks are concerned. Their unfortunate, under-parented off-spring mess about with these gifts, and don't make very much of them, and put
            them away; and you see their consequences in after-life in the weakly-conceived villas and suburbs that people have build all round London.</p>
            <p>Such poor, under-nourished nurseries must needs fall back upon the Encyclo-pædia Britannica, and even that is becoming flexible and on 
            India paper! But our box of bricks almost satisfies. With our box of bricks we can scheme and build, all three of us, for the best part 
            of an hour, and still have more bricks in the box.</p>
            <p>So much now for the bricks. I will tell later how we use cartridge-paper and card and other things to help in our building, and of the
            decorative use we make of pas-ticine. Of course, it goes without saying that we despise those foolish, expensive, made-up wooden and 
            pasteboard castles that are sold in shops; playing with them is like playing with somebody else's dead<cb/>
            game in a state of <hi rendition="simple:italic">rigor mortis</hi>. Let me now say a little about toy soldiers and the world to which they
            belong.</p>
            <p><rs type="soldier">Toy soldiers used to be flat, small crea-tures in my own boyhood, in comparison with the magnificent beings one can buy to-day. There 
            has been an enormous im-provement in our national physique in this respect. Now they can stand nearly two inches high and look you broadly
            in the face, and they have the movable arms and alert in-telligence of scientifically exercised men. You get five of them mounted or nine
            afoot in a box for <measure type="currency">tenpence halfpenny</measure>. We three like those of British manufacture best&#8212;other makes are of incompatible sizes.</rs> And
            we have a rule that saves much trouble&#8212;that all redcoats belong to G. P. Wells, and all other-colored coats to F. R. Wells&#8212;
            all gifts, bequests, and accidents notwithstand-ing. Also we have sailors; but, since there are no red-coated sailors, blue counts as red.</p>
            <p>Then we have Beef-eaters, Red Indians, Zulus, for whom there are special rules. We find we can buy lead dogs, cats, lions,
            tigers, horses, camels, cattle, and elephants of a reasonably corresponding size, and we have also several boxes of railway porters,
            and some soldiers we bought in Hesse-Darmstadt that we pass off on an unsus-<pb/>
               pecting home world as policemen. But we want civilians very badly. <rs type="soldier">We found a box of German civilians once in a shop in Oxford Street
                  near the Marble Arch, the right size but rather heavy, and running nearly to <measure type="currency">twopence halfpenny apiece</measure> (which is too dear): gentleman,
            ladies in gray and white, two children and a dog, and so on&#8212;but we have never been able to find any more.</rs> Will toy manufacturers
            please note? I write now as if I were British Consul-General in Toyland, noting new opportunities for trade.</p>
            <p><rs type="soldier">Consequent upon this dearth, our little world suffers from an exaggerated curse of militarism, and even the grocer wears epau-lettes.
            This might please the War Depart-ment, but it certainly does not please us. I wish indeed that we could buy boxes of<cb/>
            tradesmen: a blue butcher, a white baker with a loaf of standard bread, a draper or so, boxes of servants, boxes of street traffic, smart
            sets, and so forth. We could do with a judge and barristers, or a box of vestry-men. It is true that we can buy Salvation Army lasses
            and football players, but we are cold to both of these. We have, of course, boy scouts. With such boxes of civilians we could have much
            more fun than with the running, marching, swashbuckling soldiery that pervades us. They drive us to reviews, and it is only emperors
            and kings and very silly small boys who can take an undying interest in uniforms and reviews.</rs></p>
            <p><rs type="train">And, lastly, of our railways let me merely remark here that we have always insisted upon one uniform gauge. We have adhered rigidly
            to gauge o, and everything we buy<pb n="747"/>
            fits into and develops our existing railway system. Nothing is more indicative of a wambling sort of parent and a coterie of witless, 
            worthless uncles, than a heap of railway toys of different gauges and natures in the children's play-room.</rs> And so, hav-ing told you
            of the material we have, let me now tell you of one or two games (out of innumerably many) that we have played. Of course in this
            I have to be a little arti-ficial. Actual games of the kind I am illus-trating here have been played by us, many and many a time, with 
            joy and happy in-vention and no thought of publication. They have gone now, those games, into that vaguely luminous and iridescent
            world of memories into which all love-engendering happiness must go. But we have tried our best to set them out again and recall
            the good points in them here.</p>
         </div>

      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
